Okay, good morning. This is Rabbi Matisyahu דף ק"ח. Daf Kuf-Chet.
Yesterday, we sort of got up onto the top of ק"ח, Kuf-Chet,
but really the next thing on ק"ח Kuf-Chet is a continuation of
the case story we had at the bottom of ק"ז, Kuf-Zayin, so
we should go back to there.
Five lines up from the bottom of ק"ז. Kuf-Zayin. רבה בר רב
הונא הוה ליה ההוא אבא גודא דנהרא. Rabba bar Rav Huna hava
lei hahu aba guda denahara. רבה בר רב
הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna was the owner of a forest that
was on the side of a river. אמרו
ליה ניקוץ מר. Amru lei nekutz mar. And they said to him,
you should, you know, you should chop down the area on the
side of the river because people need to use that for pulling
their barges along the river. אמר להו קוצו עילאי ותתאי והדר ניקוץ
אנא. Amar lehu kotzu ilai vetatai vehadar nekutz ana. He said, I’m
not going to do that. There are other people nearby me; they
need to do it first, and then I’ll go along with it,
which sounds a little curmudgeonly to me. Ah, but it wasn’t. היכי
עביד הכי? Heichi avid hachi? How can he do that, says the
גמרא? Gemara? The גמרא Gemara also thinks it’s problematic. והכתיב התקוששו וקושו?
Vehaktiv hitkoshshu vakoshu? Gather yourselves and then gather. ואמר ריש לקיש, Veamar
Reish Lakish, that means קשוט עצמך ואחר כך קשוט אחרים. Kshot atzmecha
veachar kach kshot acherim. Take care of yourself first, do what you
need to do first. Here it’s about adorning yourself, literally. ואחר כך
קשוט אחרים, Veachar kach kshot acherim,
and then you should deal with other people. התם אבא דבי פרזק
רופילא הוה.
Hatam aba devei Parzak
Rofila hava. What’s the problem? That the rest of the forest was
owned by a guy named Parzak, was owned by Parzak, who was
a Persian general of some sort.
ואמר אי קייצו קייצנא ואי לא קייצו אמאי איקוץ?
Veamar ei kaitzu kaitzna veei lo
kaitzu amai ekutz? It’s owned by another person. I can’t expect him
to go along with what I do. הני דמחיי להו אשלי לא
מסתגיי להו. Hani demachai lehu ashlei lo mistagai lehu. The underlying notion
of התקוששו וקושו hitkoshshu vakoshu is that other people will do it
or that I can have an impact on them. But I don’t
have any, I’m not going to have any impact on Parzak. ודידי
לא מסתגיי להו, Vedidi lo mistagai lehu, and so it has to
be that he’s going to do it first, and then if he
does it, I’ll deal with it. For the moment, the other side
of the river is owned by other people. That’s already cut, they
already have space to pull the barges along the other side. They’re
not just because my little piece of forest on the side of
the river is cut down and they have space, they’re not going
to move over to the other side for forty feet to drag
their barges on my side. They’re going to stay on the side
that’s fully cut down. ודידי לא
מסתגיי להו, Vedidi lo mistagai lehu, and so I’m going to leave
it as it is. א רבה בר רב נחמן הוה קאזיל בארבא.
Rabba bar Rav Nachman
hava ka’azil bearba. חזא ההוא אבא דקאי אגודא דנהרא. Chaza hahu aba
dekai aguda denahara. He saw such a forest that doesn't have the
area by the river cut down. אמר להו דמאן? Amar lehu deman?
He asked whose is it? אמרו
ליה דרבה בר רב הונא. Amru lei de-Rabba bar Rav Huna. So
now we’ve established that there’s this issue with רבה בר רב הונא
Rabba bar Rav Huna from the bottom of the last page, who
refused to cut down the part of his forest that was on
the side of the river. רבה בר רב נחמן Rabba bar Rav
Nachman was traveling and he saw such a forest, and he asked
whose is it? Ah, it’s רבה בר רב הונא. Rabba bar Rav
Huna. He responds, רבה
בר רב נחמן Rabba bar Rav Nachman doesn’t like this, he responds:
אמר יד השרים והסגנים הייתה במעל הזה ראשונה. Amar yad hasarim vehasganim
hayta bamaal haze rishona. The hand of the officers and the other
officers was in unfaithfulness at the first. אמר
להו קוצו קוצו.
Amar lehu kotzu
kotzu.
He says, you should cut, cut.
אתא רבה בר רב הונא אשכחיה דקייץ. Ata Rabba bar Rav Huna
ashkechei dekaitz. He found that they cut down. אמר מאן קייץ ליקצו
ענפיה. Amar man kaitz liktzu anafia.
רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna is really unhappy that
they came and cut down his, they came and cut down the
part of his forest. He knew that it was unnecessary, and he
knew that he knew that whatever required him to do it didn’t
really apply to him because of his special situation. And he says,
the one who cut it, his branches should be cut off. Branches,
רש"י Rashi explains, means his children shouldn’t survive, which is very harsh.
אמרי
כולהו שני דרבה בר רב הונא לא אקיים ליה זרעא לרבה בר
רב נחמן.
Amri kulehu shenei de-Rabba bar Rav
Huna lo akayem lei zara le-Rabba bar Rav Nachman. And the entire
time that רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna was alive,
his, none of the children of רבה בר רב נחמן, Rabba bar
Rav Nachman, who was the person who told them to cut down
the area, the part of רבה בר רב הונא’s Rabba bar Rav
Huna forest, did not survive.
Sorry, why, why was he so upset about this?
He didn’t want to cut down his, he didn’t want that part
of his forest cut down. I don’t know, it doesn’t say.
Because he cursed him, because he felt that the leaders should be
the exemplar, the exemplifier of how to do whatever.
That’s possible. Yeah, but he told this other Rabbi who was also
one of
the leaders.
I don’t think
it
explains. רבה בר רב נחמן, Rabba bar Rav Nachman, who is the
one who discovers this forest that doesn’t have the area by the
river cut down, is the one who says יד השרים. yad hasarim.
It does not explain why רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav
Huna didn’t want to cut it down. He knew that it was
unnecessary for him to cut it down, and so he didn’t want
it to be cut down. Presumably he enjoyed having that part of
the forest near the river. He didn’t want to have it be
הפקר, hefker, which is essentially what it, what it ought to be.
It’s כאילו ke’ilu it should have been רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, although
it’s not, as we saw yesterday, it’s not properly רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim a public domain because רשות הרבים reshut harabbim in the classic
sense is a street where all people have access, and this was
not a street where all people have access and need space to
move past each other.
It’s a
different...
What do you make of this in terms of like equality? In
other words, we get so involved with like going to court and
dealing with smaller
improprieties one person does to another. Here was like for his trees
he's cursing somebody that that people should be killed.
Yes, it's—
What do you make of that?
I don't. It's not equitable. And it seems it seems extreme. It
is extreme.
And it happens in other stories too where they talk about it
seems like other places where people get curses and then you know
family members die or something like
that. Right.
I don't have an answer.
Okay.
Another thing.
Actually don't know what this fits with here except we're dealing—I do
know. We're dealing here still with sort of public domain issues and
what do we have to do where we're sharing space with other
people? Sharing space with other people, sharing public space with the entire,
with everybody.
That's—that was the deal with the space of the forest along the
river where we have to cut it down to leave room for
people to move their barges.
We dealt a little, we dealt a little with private shared space
where we had the tree on the מיצרא, Meitzra,
where how do you split it when it's on the mound that
separates the two fields?
Here we're dealing with just sort of like a city issue. What
do you have to do about the wall? אמר רב יהודה הכל
לאיגלי גפא ואפילו מיתמי אבל רבנן לא. Amar Rav Yehuda hakkol le-iglei
gappa va-afillu mi-ytamei aval rabbanan lo.
Rav Yehuda says everybody has to be involved in fixing the wall
or closing the gate, even orphans. רבנן, Rabbanan, the rabbis don't have
to. מאי טעמא רבנן לא צריכי נטירותא וקאיי דפצחא ואפילו מרבנן.
Mai ta-ama? Rabbanan lo tzerikhei netiruta
ve-ka-ei de-patzcha ve-afillu me-rabbanan.
The reason that the rabbis don't have to be involved in fixing
the wall or closing the gate is because they don't require to
be—they don't need to be guarded. God guards them presumably, they think
is what sort of the implication of that is.
They don't have to be—they don't have to be gated or
they don't— They don't have to be involved in dealing with the
gate or the wall of the city because they themselves do not
require that sort of guarding. They don't need that protection.
But they're benefiting from it, don't they?
It says that they don't. That is the implication.
The presumption is that the rabbis don't need to be guarded. God
guards them.
What about the rest of the people?
The rest of the people...
The point is
they share the burden. Not everybody has to deal with it. I
understand that in reality—that like, in the reality that we experience, there's
no difference between a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham who lives in a
guarded city and anybody else who lives in a guarded city.
They all benefit—everyone in the city will be guarded
because of the wall.
No, לאו הכי. Lav hachi.
They all benefit from the wall, they all benefit from the soldier
standing outside.
But what the גמרא Gemara says, no, the rabbis have their Torah,
the rabbis have their own זכות Zechut that protects them. They have
their own merit that God is involved in their protection. They have—מה
איכפת להו? Mah ikhpat lehu? What does it matter to them if
there's a wall around the city? So we can't require them to
be involved in putting the wall around the city. Everybody else,
including—including orphans who normally would not have to be involved in such
a public issue, do have to be involved in this particular thing.
To us, this does not look equitable, but within the metaphysical presumptions
of the גמרא Gemara it does.
And that's what we're seeing. מאי טעמא רבנן לא צריכי נטירותא וקאיי
דפצחא. Mai ta-ama? Rabbanan lo tzerikhei netiruta ve-ka-ei de-patzcha. Doesn't it also
have the concept
that their study does actually protect everybody?
So that's not the concept— Well they're really doing their job, everyone
else is being protected too, right? So
I—that's why I said what I said. This concept—that concept is not
at play here. The concept at play here is they don't need
נטירותא, Netiruta, so it's not equitable to require them to be involved
in something that they don't need.
Why do—why do retirees have to pay taxes that cover schools? They
don't need education, you might say.
Why do we have to pay taxes to cover schools? We don't
send our kids— You do need—because your kids do need education. You're
choosing not to be involved in it. That's something else. That's different
between need and choosing not to use. I could say I'm a
member of this city, but it's like I don't need נטירותא, Netiruta,
I don't need a wall. But I can't—I still need it. I'm
deciding not to use the wall. The wall you can't decide not
to use. Anyway.
However, to go out and open up a well, or to fix
a מעיין Ma'ayan of some sort, to deal with the water sources,
ואפילו מרבנן, Ve-afillu me-rabbanan,
the rabbis also have to be involved in dealing with that. אה
ולא אמרן אלא דלא נפקא באכלוזא אבל באכלוזא לא דרבנן לאו בני
מיפק באכלוזא נינהו. Ah, ve-lo amran ella de-la napka be-akhloza aval be-akhloza
lo de-rabbanan lav benei mippak be-akhloza ninhu. No,
that only applies when you're actually paying somebody to go out and
do it, I believe I'm getting this right. that you're paying people
that it doesn't apply when you're going out as a group. רבנן
לאו בני נפקא נינהו. rabbanan lav bnei nafka ninhu. They aren't people
who go out and do this sort of dirty work themselves, they
pay people to do it.
Let me see what is this?
רש"י Rashi says אלא דלא נפקא באוכלוזא, ela delo nafka b'ochloza, skipping
a line to before it, דרבנן לאו בני
מיפק באוכלוזא
נינהו. derabbanan lav bnei meipak b'ochloza ninhu.
רבנן Rabbanan are not people who go out in a group, meaning
they aren't people who go out as part of a work force
to actually fix the מעיין. mayan. They are people who pay other
people to go fix the מעיין. mayan. So רבנן rabbanan are involved
in paying taxes to deal with the water sources, but they do
not need themselves to go out and fix the water source
because that's just not their כבוד. kavod. That's not that doesn't rise
to their dignity to do that themselves.
There are a number there are things all over נזיקין Nezikin where
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim or rabbis are exempt from various taxes, various
rules that generally apply to the marketplace. They're exempt here that we're
seeing from sort of public obligations. This is common in here and
we're just seeing a couple of them.
There are different reasons at play for them. Some of them is
like רבנן rabbanan help everybody, that their study helps everyone. Here we
saw the one that they don't require certain things. We saw the
ones that they have a certain level of dignity that needs to
be maintained by the law. In other places we saw that we
were concerned about their ability to go back and learn more and
so we don't require we keep we remove certain restrictions on being
involved in a marketplace from them.
Okay. אמר רב
יהודה לכרייא דנהרא,
Amar Rav
Yehuda lecharaya denahara, when you're dealing with dredging a river or fixing
the irrigation system that comes from a river, תתאי מסייע עילאי, tattai
mesayei ilai, people lower down on the river help the upper people
on the river. עילאי לא מסייע תתאי, ilai lo mesayei tattai, or
the lower down in the irrigation system so to speak. But the
עילאי ilai people higher up don't need to help the תתאי. tattai.
וחילופא במייא דמיטרא, V'chilufa b'maya demitra, but it's the opposite when you're
dealing with rainwater. So that when you're dealing with gutter systems, sewer
system, not sewer system, gutter systems,
the opposite is true, that עילאי ilai
help
the תתאי. tattai. That עילאי, ilai,
that the people higher up in the irrigation system, if they're higher
up on the hill of the city and the gutter system flows
down, so they have to go all the way down to the
bottom of the city where the gutter system ends and flows out
somewhere to make sure that that exit point is clear. But at
the very top of the city, the עילאי, ilai, the people in
the top of the hill, they're the only people in charge of
fixing that part because fixing this part of the gutter, because if
there's a flood at the top of the hill, or not a
flood, but problems in the gutter system, problems in the drainage system
at the top of the hill, people at the bottom of the
hill don't care, it's hurting people at the top of the hill.
So we don't need to help them. We need to help ourselves,
but they need to help us because helping us in this case
helps them. So there's different cases where dealing with these public works
issues applies to different people unequally. But the point the גמרא Gemara
makes here, with rainwater it's the opposite, unequal. So just to go
over it again: Dealing with dredging the river and making sure that
the irrigation system works,
the תתאי, tattai, the people at the very bottom of the irrigation
system, they no, they need to help the עילאי, ilai, they need
to go all the way up to the top of the irrigation
system.
They're only helping themselves
because that's also helping themselves, but nobody's going to come help them
at the bottom. Making sure that their part of the irrigation system,
which only affects them, is only their job alone. That's not fair.
However, the גמרא Gemara turns around, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda comes around
and says ah, but the other direction, when you're dealing with a
gutter system to get rain out, when we're at the bottom of
the city, I only have to deal with this bottom portion because
that's the part that affects me. Further up the stream, if there's
water problems and people are getting water into their homes further up
the gutter system, I don't care about that. That's their job. They
have to come help me because that needs to get out of
the city. So even though it's each one is not equitable, it
evens out because there's two different issues in the public works system
that have to be dealt with by the people of the city,
the different parts of the people of the city, in ways that
sort of even out.
Okay. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we also have a ברייתא
braita that says this. This is actually unusual for תניא נמי הכי
tanya nami hachi because it uses more language than the Amoraic statement
just did. תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami hachi comes in often in
it means we also have a ברייתא braita that teaches this. And
it usually comes in to introduce a ברייתא braita that is the
exact same wording of an Amoraic statement just given. And so academic
scholars are sort of distrustful of תניא נמי הכי tanya nami hachi
ברייתות braitot because they seem a little bit
too perfect.
And they often don't appear anywhere except the בבלי. Bavli. They don't
appear in other they don't appear in the תוספתא Tosefta sources, they
don't appear in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. This one is different insofar as
the actual language of the ברייתא braita is the teaching of the
ברייתא braita is the same, the language of the ברייתא braita is
not the same
than the one we saw in רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda statement. חמש
גנות המסתפקות מים ממעיין אחד, Chamesh ganot hamistapkot mayim mimayan echad,
five gardens or five fields that get water from a single
spring, נתקלקל המעיין nitkalkel hamayan and the spring is hurt, is ruined,
כולן מתקנות עם העליונה, kulam metaknot im ha'elyona, everybody has to help
the first person closest to the מעיין, mayan, ושל תחתונה מתקנת עם
כולן, veshel tachtona metakenet im kulan,
thus the person lowest on the chain helps everyone, ומתקנת לעצמה, umetakenet
le'atsma, but is the only person helping himself, וכן חמש חצרות שהיו
מקלחות מים לביב אחד, vechen chamesh chatserot shehayu mekalchot mayim leviv echad,
ונתקלקל הביב, venitkalkel haviv, כולן מתקנות עם התחתונה, kulam metaknot im hatachtona,
ושל עליונה מתקנת עם כולן ומתקנת לעצמה. veshel elyona metakenet im kulan
umetakenet le'atsma.
A drainage system is the inverse. Everybody has to help the last
person in the drainage system because the water needs to get out
all together, otherwise everyone's going to be backed up. But the bottom
person doesn't have to help the first person.
Good.
אמר שמואל. Amar Shmuel. Now we're going to get back to the
riverbanks and dealing with how my ownership of that area works. אמר
שמואל האי מאן דאחזיק בריתקא דנהרא חציפי הוי סלוקי לא מסלקינן ליה.
Amar Shmuel hai man de'achzik beritka denahara chatsifei havei siluki lo mesalkinan
lei.
Shmuel says somebody who like takes control, taking control here doesn't mean
that I bought it, according to the מפרשים mefarshim it means that
I paid the head tax on this. That there's a special tax
to the king of Persia, to the Persian king, not really the
Persian king, but whoever's in charge of Babylonia at the time, the
Sassanian Persians at the time, gives me some degree of title to
this land legally, even though I don't properly speaking own it according
to our laws. So if I take control of the space on
the side of the river, that's not nice because I'm keeping other
people... it's חציפי, chatsifei, it's חוצפהדיק chutzpadik is what the גמרא Gemara
says, חציפי הוי, chatsifei havei,
because I'm keeping away the space that people need to put their
boats, explains רש״י. Rashi. סלוקי לא מסלקינן ליה, Siluki lo mesalkinan lei,
but we don't kick him out. האידנא דקא כתיב פרסאי קני לך
עד מלא צווארי סוסיא מיא. Haidana deka kativ Parsai kani lach ad
melo tsavarei susya maya.
However,
now that we now later on from Shmuel when the Persians have
created a contract or we have adopted a Persian contract that says
you have the rights to space up to the point where a
horse is up to its neck in the river, so essentially my
domain on the side of the river extends into the river and
so for somebody to go and be on my land is a
problem, to be on the side of the river is a problem.
סלוקי נמי מסלקינן ליה, Siluki nami mesalkinan lei,
we kick them out now. אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. So
that's just a change in a seemingly a historical change about whether
it's possible within הלכה Halacha for somebody to take illegal control of
the land on the side of the river. Eventually we conclude that
later on because the way deeds are written on the side of
the river is that it extends into the river, the space on
the side of the river is mine. I have obligations to the
public to keep it clear because that's the wharfing area, that's the
place where, yeah,
כאילו, ke'ilu, yeah, yeah.
But I own it.
So if somebody else goes there, then he's removed?
Yes. If somebody else tries to take control of that space because
it's כאילו ke'ilu public and he says I'm going to take control
of it, that's not only is that חוצפהדיק, chutzpadik, it's not okay,
we also kick you off. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב האי מאן
דאחזיק בין אחי ובין שותפי חציפי הוי סלוקי לא מסלקינן ליה. Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav hai man de'achzik bein achai uvein shutfei chatsifei
havei siluki lo mesalkinan lei.
Rav says that somebody
who takes land from among brothers or among partners, that's also חוצפהדיק,
chutzpadik, but we don't kick them off, סלוקי לא מסלקינן ליה. siluki
lo mesalkinan lei. רב נחמן אמר נמי מסלקינן ליה, Rav Nachman amar
nami mesalkinan lei, we also kick them off. ואי משום דינא דבר
מצרא לא מסלקינן ליה, Vei mishum dina devar metsara lo mesalkinan lei,
but we don't kick somebody off because of the דינא דבר מצרא,
dina devar metsara, which is what we're getting into in a moment.
The rest of our דף daf is going to be about דינא
דבר מצרא, dina devar metsara, which I'll explain what it is in
a moment. We don't kick them out. נהרדעי אמרי אפילו משום דינא
דבר מצרא מסלקינן ליה. Naharda'ei amri afilu mishum dina devar metsara mesalkinan
lei. We also do kick we do kick people out because of
the דינא דבר מצרא dina devar metsara משום שנאמר ועשית הישר והטוב
בעיני
השם.
mishum shene'emar ve'asita hayashar vehatov be'einei
Hashem. Okay, so what's דינא דבר מצרא? dina devar metsara? The בר
מצרא, bar metsara, we saw already that the מצרא metsara is literally
the border mound between the two fields. A בר מצרא bar metsara
is somebody who owns the field next to mine. So when I
have one field and there are people around me, ideally like if
they're looking for more land to buy they're not going to go
buy it ten miles away, ten miles down the road, they'd ideally
like to buy my land and extend their field into mine. And
so we say ועשית הישר והטוב. ve'asita hayashar vehatov. The verse in
the תורה Torah that says you shall do the good and upright
thing, the חכמים chachamim explain that that means in our case that
if that the neighbor has the right of first refusal to the
degree that in many cases if I the owner of the central
piece of land go and sell land to another person entirely who's
not near here, who doesn't who isn't the בר מצרא, bar metsara,
then I've done something wrong and the בר מצרא bar metsara has
the right to come to that new owner and say you know
what really you didn't own that, here's the money, go away.
He has the בר מצרא, Bar Metzar, the neighbor has the right
to kick that person off. That, and I think it's also explained
that this person who bought the land, again, against the ועשית הישר
והטוב, Veasita Hayashar Vehatov, he did it in an improper way, was
also because the way דינא דבר מצרא, Dina DeBar Metzar, דינא דבר
מצרא Dina DeBar Metzar is put into place, is acting as the
agent of the דינא Dina of the בר מצרא. Bar Metzar.
Which is why he's able to go and say, "Here's the money,
go away." Now, אמר
ליה, Amar Lei,
so somebody comes and says. We're dealing with, we have the case
of the field that's among other fields owned by other people. A
customer comes and says to one of the בר מצרא, Bar Metzar,
אמר ליה, Amar Lei, "איזיל איזבון, Izil Izbun,
can I go and buy that field? Is that okay with you?"
He tries to get permission. ואמר ליה, Veamar Lei, "זיל זבון," Zil
Zbun, and he says, "Yeah, go ahead, buy the field." צריך למיקני
מיניה או לא? Tzarich Lemiknei Minei O Lo? The question is, does
he still need to make קנין? Kinyan? Does he still need to
have
to acquire it from the בר מצרא? Bar Metzar? The בר מצרא
Bar Metzar had the right of first refusal, and when I'm buying
out from under a בר מצרא, Bar Metzar, I'm acting as his
agent. Do I need to make a... to own it, do I
need to do a further thing? רבינא
אמר לא צריך למיקני
מיניה, נהרדעי אמרי צריך למיקני מיניה. Ravina
Amar Lo Tzarich Lemiknei
Minei, Nahardai Amrei Tzarich Lemiknei Minei.
There's a מחלוקת Machloket between רבינא Ravina and נהרדעי. Nahardai. והלכתא צריך
למיקני מיניה, Vehilchata Tzarich Lemiknei Minei,
and the גמרא Gemara concludes, at least in this version, that he
does need to make a קנין. Kinyan. Why? Why... remind me...
is he turning into an agent here? כי, Ki, the way that
this is explained is that, let's say there's a field... I don't
need the picture for this. I own a piece of land. You're
my neighbor, David's my neighbor. Okay. Michael comes in and buys land
out from under you. You have the right to kick him off
by giving him the money and saying go away. The reason that
you can do that is that when Michael came and bought the
land, כאילו, Keilu,
he was acting as your agent when he did that.
It's not especially important to this, I think that's like some way
in which the idea is explained that I'm able... that you're able
to just kick him off. But then it becomes my land
and I don't need to buy it.
You have to buy it, you have to buy it from him,
but there is no דיון Diyun involved, I think is what it
points to, but let's not get all too into that because it's
not important to understand the גמרא Gemara for the moment. Okay. The
question is, however, now רש״י Rashi explains this last thing about, do
I need to make... does the... when the לוקח, Lokeach, when this
outside customer comes, when the outside person comes in, buys out from
under the בר מצרא Bar Metzar with permission from the בר מצרא,
Bar Metzar, with permission from the neighbor, does he need קנין? Kinyan?
We say no. רש״י Rashi explains why. מצי אמר ליה משטי הייתי
בך. Matzi Amar Lei Mashti Hayiti Bach.
I can say I was kidding. How do you know that I
was being serious?
I wasn't being serious... I have the right to this until really
the end of it. Other people, we also explain at the end
of the day, I think רמב״ם Rambam says this, that if he
bought it and then he got permission, there's no idea... there's no
issue that he might have been kidding. I already bought it. At
this point it needs to be, "Do you want this or not?"
I bought this without your permission, I bought this out from under
you and you didn't have right of first refusal and you say
"That's okay," that's the end of the story, you no longer have
rights. Okay.
והלכתא צריך למיקני מיניה. Vehilchata Tzarich Lemiknei Minei. Now
that we've said, now that we've concluded that he needs to make
קנין, Kinyan, אי לא קני מיניה אי יקר וזל ברשותיה,
Ei Lo Kani Minei Ei
Yakar Vezal Birshutei, that's your fault. אזבן במאה ושוי מאתן. Izvan Beme'ah
Veshavyei Matan. If this outside person came and bought something for a
hundred that was really worth two hundred units, חזינא, Hazina, we make
an evaluation. אי לכולי
עלמא קא מוזלי וזבין בהכי,
Ei Lekuli
Alma Ka Muzlei Vezavin Behai, if the owner of the
central field would have sold it for this same low price of
a hundred, half off, for everybody. He needed to get out of
here fast, he was selling all of his stuff for half off...
not all of the stuff, all of his stuff is a different
case, as we'll see on the next page. He was selling this
field, half off. I'm done with
this part of the world, I'm leaving. This field, half off. Okay.
Then when the בר מצרא Bar Metzar comes and wants to kick
off the לוקח, Lokeach, when the neighbor comes and wants to kick
off this third party, he can buy it for a hundred. He
can buy it for the half-off price. יהיב ליה מאה ושקיל ליה,
ואי לא יהיב ליה מאתן ושקיל ליה. Yehav Lei Me'ah Veshakil Lei,
Ve'ei Lo Yehav Lei Matan Veshakil Lei.
If really there was a special relationship
between the בר מצרא... Bar Metzar... between the outside person and the
owner of the central field that he was giving him a deal
for a hundred, when the בר מצרא Bar Metzar wants to come
and kick off the new owner of the field, the owner of
the field... Has bought a two hundred זוז zuz field, half of
which was כאילו ke-ilu a gift from the original owner, and so
when the neighbor wants to come and kick off this new person,
he has to pay this new owner two hundred to take control
of this field for himself. זבנה במאתן ושויא מאה, Zavanh be-matai u-shavei
me'ah,
what about the opposite? What if he bought it for two hundred
but it was really only worth
one hundred? סבר
מיניה מצי
אמינא
ליה לתיקוני שדרתך ולא לעוותי.
Savar minei matzi amina lei
letikuni
shedartach velo
le'avutei. It's easy then you can say to him, I'm trying to
do right by you. I'm not sure exactly what this, to fix,
to fix your spine and not to make it, to not to
make it crooked. אמר ליה מר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לרב אשי,
Amar lei Mar Kashisha brei de-Rav Chisda le-Rav Ashi, הכי אמרינן נהרדעי
משום דרב נחמן אין אונאה לקרקעות. Hachi amrinan naharda'ei mishum de-Rav Nachman
ein ona'ah le-karka'ot. Really what this means, Mar
Kashisha, son of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, sister of רב אשי, Rav
Ashi, this is actually what the נהרדעי Naharda'ei say in the name
of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, there is no אונאה, ona'ah, there is
no price gouging in terms of קרקעות. karka'ot. And so
when I come and that really he overpaid for it, that this
new לוקח loke'ach overpaid for it,
and so at the end of the day in
פרק יד הלכה ה, Perek yud daled halacha hey,
yeah,
at the end of the day he still needs to pay two
hundred because there's no אונאה ona'ah and that's what the, that's what
the value is even though it seems to be misvalued.
Okay,
now we have a new issue
in the issue of בר מצרא, bar meitzra, which is that there
are cases now we're going to deal with the cases where בר
מצרא bar meitzra doesn't apply. We've gone through and we've established
some of the contours of how בר מצרא bar meitzra works, how
it works from somebody from the central field, their neighbors, and somebody
wants to buy it out from under him, what does the בר
מצרא bar meitzra have to do, what does the neighbor have to
do to gain control, when does he have to pay more, when
does he have to pay less, what has to be done for
the third party to actually take control of the field
properly? Here we're going to deal with where the דינא דבר מצרא
dina de-bar meitzra doesn't apply at all, where there's no issue, where
there's no right of
presumption, there's no right of first refusal. זבין ליה גריוא דארעא במצעי
נכסי, Zavin lei geriva de-ara be-metzai nikhsei,
if I sell a person, if I sell this third party
a strip of land in the middle of mine, so it's not
on either side, I'm not really the בר מצרא, bar meitzra, he's
not really בר מצרא bar meitzra
because it's in the middle. חזינן אי עידי היא אי זיבורית היא,
Chazinan ee idi hi ee ziborti hi, we see whether that piece
of land that he sold was of a distinct quality from the
rest of the field. Is it particularly good, is it particularly bad?
זבינא זבינא, zavina zavina,
if it is one of those, if it is distinct from the
rest of the field, that's okay, זבינא זבינא. zavina zavina. ואי לא
הערמה היא,
Ve-ee la ha'aramah
hi, that's הערמה, ha'aramah, that's a loophole in the system and we
don't like that.
What does that mean? If I had a field, what would be
the הערמה ha'aramah that I just did? If I bought a strip
of land that's the same as the rest of the land in
the middle of the field, then I've become the בר מצרא bar
meitzra of the central field, and then I want to buy this
land and this land and this land, and suddenly I've gotten around
the whole issue of the right of the first refusal by buying
in the middle and then buying up the rest of the field.
Because once I was in the middle of the field, I had
the right of the first refusal on the rest of the field.
However, if I take a strip of land, so that's a problem,
we don't like that. If there's a strip of land that's distinct
from the rest of it, I don't become the בר מצרא bar
meitzra on anything else because that land is different. And so that's
unproblematic and this strip of land would have been sold separately in
any
event. Another point, מתנה ליתא משום דינא דבר מצרא, Matanah leita mishum
dina de-bar meitzra, a gift that I give to someone else
doesn't have, doesn't, the, I can give a gift to somebody without
a right of first refusal. I don't have to go and say
to my neighbor, I want to give this to my friend, he
doesn't say I want to buy it from you. It's my right
to give what I have to give.
Talking about land.
If I have a land, with a, I have a piece of
land, you're my neighbor, you would have, if I were selling it,
you would have right of first refusal, but I'm giving it to
somebody,
you would not.
אי כתב ליה אחריות, Ee katav lei achrayut, if there's a contract
that has אחריות achrayut in it, what's אחריות? achrayut? Yeah, yeah,
if it has different rules about this piece of land, that's not
really a מתנה, matanah, explains רשי, Rashi, and so even though I'm
giving it to you, but I'm giving you this as a backdrop
for as a
backdrop. לית בה משום דינא
דבר
מצרא.
Leit bah mishum Dina d'Bar
Metza.
מכר כל נכסיו לאחד. Macha kol nechasav l'echad. If I'm selling all
of my properties to a third party, then the דינא דבר מצרא
Dina d'Bar Metza doesn't apply.
רש"י Rashi explains, I have a lot of fields in a number
of places, מכר כל נכסיו לאחד, macha kol nechasav l'echad, בכל מקום
שהן, b'chol makom shehen, זו במזרח וזו במערב, zo b'mizrach v'zo b'maarav,
ואתו מצרני חד v'atu matzrani chad מהן בערעור, mehen b'irur,
and somebody comes and says, "Hey, you can't sell this. I'm the
בר מצרא, Bar Metza, I have right of first refusal," לית בה
משום דינא דבר מצרא, leit bah mishum Dina d'Bar Metza, שלא תקנו
חכמים, shelo tiknu chachamim,
there's no תקנה takkana of בר מצרא Bar Metza doesn't apply. לוקח
להסתלק לעשות הישר והטוב לבעל המצר, lokeach l'histalek la'asot hayashar v'hatov l'ba'al
hametzar, שהוא רע למוכר, shehu ra l'mocher, שלא יקנה השאר, shelo yikneh
hashar, שימשוך ידו בשבילו, sheyimshoch yado bishvilo, למקום שדה דמצר, l'makom sadeh
d'metzar, לא תיקון דינא
דבר מצרא.
lo tikun
Dina d'Bar Metza. That if somebody is trying to sell his entire
worth, I'm trying to sell everything I have, it would hurt me
as the owner of this field to not be able to sell
all of my property to another party just because somebody's going to
come and be מערער m'arer on one side
in another place. Some of it is in צפת, Tzfat, some of
it is in טבריה, Tveryah, some of it is in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
some of it is in ירוחם. Yerucham. It's like,
just because somebody in ירושלים Yerushalayim is going to come say, "Hey,
wait, I have right of first refusal,"
no, it's like this is, I'm trying to sell everything and my
ability to sell everything is more important than your, than the עשית
הישר והטוב, asita hayashar v'hatov, the doing the right thing by you.
We also need to do the right thing by me. עשית הישר
והטוב asita hayashar v'hatov can't come in the way of my loss,
and when I'm selling everything at once, that's my
loss. דינא דבר מצרא Dina d'Bar Metza works that there's no loss
to me. I'm just selling it for the same price to somebody
else, which is why the price differences mattered
before.
Maybe it's that you can get a better price because you're bundling
all the properties together.
I don't know that it's a better price, but it's that I
want to sell everything as one. I'm leaving the country.
Maybe you can't sell the other stuff unless this piece is part
of the bundle.
Perhaps, or I can't sell this
piece. Yeah, that's probably the way it is, is that I can't
sell.
If it doesn't affect what you can get for the rest of
it,
then
it's no harm, no foul, and you're no worse off if you
sell one parcel to the neighbor.
Right, right. But I think the rule applies whether that's the case
or not, that we've just taken away the דינא דבר מצרא Dina
d'Bar Metza in that
case. Now
because
דינא דבר מצרא Dina d'Bar Metza is like a תקנת חכמים, takkant
chachamim, but it's a תקנת חכמים takkant chachamim that sort of has
its basis in a verse, and the verse is sort of a
general rule, ועשית הישר והטוב. v'asita hayashar v'hatov. So we might still
say in a real case where it's perfectly fine for me to
sell that separately, you know, it's not right for you to get
away for you
to kill someone's right of first refusal. You should really go to
them first if you can. If it can work out, it's better
that way. It doesn't mean it's not better, just means that there's
no חיוב chiyuv to do it.
Okay. זבן מעכום וזבין לעכום, zavan m'akum v'zavin l'akum,
לית בה משום דינא דבר מצרא, leit bah mishum Dina d'Bar Metza,
for different reasons. If I buy from a non-Jewish person or I
sell to a non-Jewish person, then there's no issue of בר מצרא.
Bar Metza.
Why? זבן מעכום, zavan m'akum, if I bought from an עכום akum
and I bought instead and I got out of the way, I
got past the right of first refusal of the
neighbor, דאמר ליה אריא אברחי לך ממצרך, d'amar leh arya avrachi lach
mimitzrach, I've gotten rid of a lion from your border and I've
got, you didn't want that neighbor anyway and I got rid of
your neighbor. זבין לעכום, zavin l'akum, עכום ודאי לאו בר עשית הישר
והטוב הוא. akum vadda'i lav bar asita hayashar v'hatov hu.
Ah, but if I sold to an
עכום, akum, the חיוב chiyuv that underlies דינא דבר מצרא Dina d'Bar
Metza is an עשה. aseh. It's a positive obligation of the תורה,
Torah, and those positive obligations of the תורה Torah don't apply to
non-Jews. He's not a בר, bar, he's not part of the rules
that say do the good and the upright, and so there's no
problem. However, שמתיה
באדי מצר מיתמנא ליה, shamtei b'adei metzar mitmana leh, we've put him
in חרם, cherem, a certain kind of חרם, cherem, עד דמקבל עליה
כל אונסא דאתי ליה מחמתיה, ad d'mekabel leh kol onsa d'ati leh
machmatei, until I have to deal with all the problems that come
with having put a non-Jew in this area. So we're all, so
your neighbor's going to suffer, we're going to make you suffer in
the same
way. משכנתא, mashkanta, if something is
a mortgage is already mortgaged, לית בה משום דינא דבר מצרא, leit
bah mishum Dina d'Bar Metza, then there's no issue of בר מצרא
Bar Metza in selling it. דאמר רב אשי אמרו לי סבי דמתא
מחסיא, d'amar Rav Ashi amru li Sabei d'Mata Mechasya, רב אשי Rav
Ashi explains that the old men of מתא מחסיא Mata Mechasya said,
מאי משכנתא דשכונה גביה, mai mashkanta d'shchuna gabei, what is mortgaged
property? It's as if that the person it's mortgaged to is already
like your neighbor. מאי
נפקא מינה, mai nafka mina, what's the point of that? What is
that? Okay, so far so good. You had a little cute... saying
about משכנתא Mashkanta that a משכון Mashkon sounds like שכן Shachen because
it has the same root. But what's the practical difference? מאי נפקא
מינה? Mai nafka mina? לדינא דבר מצרא L'dina d'bar metra that this
applies that he is actually your neighbor so far as דינא דבר
מצרא dina d'bar metra goes. לזבוני ברחיק ולמיזבן בקירוב, Lizvoni
berachik ulemizban bekirov, לזבוני
בזיבורא ולמיזבן בעידית, Lizvoni bezibura ulemizban be'idit, לית בה משום דינא דבר
מצרא.
Leit
bah
mishum dina
d'bar metra. To sell
far away in order to buy closer or to sell bad land
in order to buy good land, there is no issue of דינא
דבר מצרא. dina d'bar metra. What does that mean? רש"י Rashi explains:
אם מוכר זה מוכרח מפני שהיא רחוקה ממנו ורוצה לקנות אחרת בקרוב.
Im mocher zeh muchrach mipnei shehi rechoka mimenu verotze liknot acheret bekarov.
I own land far away. I don't want to work that land.
I don't want to be in charge of that land anymore. People
do this all the time.
They're limiting דינא דבר מצרא dina d'bar metra because it's the בר
מצרא bar metra is based on ועשית הישר והטוב, Ve'asita hayashar vehatov,
doing the right thing. So when is the right thing the right
thing? לית בה משום דינא, Leit bah mishum dina, לפי שאין לנו
להפסיד מוכר משום טוב וישר. Lefi she'ein lanu lehafsid mocher mishum tov
veyashar. It's like if there's a loss to the seller, that's not
good either. משום טוב וישר
דמצרא.
Mishum tov
veyashar dematzra. It's like there's no argument of טוב וישר tov veyashar
of good and uprightness
that can make me להפסיד מוכר, lehafsid mocher, לפי שאין לנו להפסיד
מוכר משום טוב וישר דמצרא דכשם שעלינו לעשות טוב לזה כך עלינו
לעשות טוב לזה.
Lefi she'ein lanu lehafsid mocher mishum
tov veyashar dematzra decheshem she'aleinu la'asot tov lazeh kach aleinu la'asot tov
lazeh.
We have to be equitable. בר מצרא Bar metra is a rule
of equity that it's unfair to the neighbor that somebody else should
have first rights to a land that would improve his, but not
in every case. There are times when it's also
not equitable to put that rule in place to the person trying
to sell the land.
The same case with I'm trying to get rid of bad land
apparently.
Okay,
next point. Now
we
get into different issues. לכרגא ולמזוני ולקבורה. L'karga ulemezoni ulikvura. If I
need to sell it to pay the head tax, or I need
to sell it to support widows, to support alimony, to buy food
for other people that I'm required to buy food for because of
a family issue, ולקבורה, ulikvura, or to pay for burying somebody. We're
going to note these are all three very different things. כרגא Karga
is something where there's a problem that I have because the sort
of the rulers of this country that I'm in require me to
pay a tax. Everybody needs to pay a tax.
ומזוני, Umezonei, I'm contractually obligated and I'm obligated מתקנתא דרבנן mitakanata derabbanan
to support these people, and so I have to pay for their
upkeep. ולקבורה, Ulikvura, I'm biblically obligated to be involved, everyone is biblically
obligated I think on some level to do קבורה, kevura, but I'm
also obligated to bury somebody. There's more of a, we might call
an אורח חיים Orach Chayim thing, that we have חושן משפט, Choshen
Mishpat, אבן העזר, Even Ha'ezer, and אורח חיים Orach Chayim coming into
play where I have
to,
אורח
חיים Orach Chayim being for that I sort of have a ritual
obligation to bury somebody. I have an אבן העזר Even Ha'ezer obligation
through my contracts, through my family obligations to take care of people,
and I sort of I have a personal financial obligation to pay
the poll tax. לית בה משום דינא דבר מצרא. Leit bah mishum
dina d'bar metra. And thus in those three situations where there's another
obligation butting up against it, the issue of ועשית הישר והטוב ve'asita
hayashar vehatov doesn't come into play. It's still okay and good to
sell this land and get out of the right of first refusal
of the neighbor.
דאמרי נהרדעי, De'amri Neharde'i, we cite as a source, לכרגא למזוני ולקבורה
מזבינינן בלא אכרזתא. L'karga lemezoni ulikvura mazbininan bela achrazta. For when I'm
paying the poll tax or I'm paying for alimony or I'm paying
for the burial of somebody, we sell without announcing it. I can
sell and nobody has the right to come in and get it
except for the person I want to sell it to. לאישה וליתמי
ולשותפי, L'isha uleyatmei uleshutfei, if I'm selling to a woman or to
orphans
or to partners, לית בה משום דינא דבר מצרא. leit bah mishum
dina d'bar metra. There's different reasons for this.
For a woman, רש"י Rashi explains
and רמב"ם Rambam also adopts the same point that in the time
that these תקנות takanot are being created, it's not אורח ארעא orach
ar'a for a woman to go out and look for the best
deal. And so
if a woman is going to buy land then she's going to
buy whatever she gets to first, they presume, and so they make
the rule of דינא דבר מצרא dina d'bar metra that she can
undermine the right of first refusal of the neighbor because it's the
first land she found that was for sale.
יתמי Yatmei is different,
orphans
are different. It's just simply not
חסד. chesed. שכינא דמתא ושכינא דסדא. Shechina de-mata ve-Shechina de-sada. And
now we're moving from the issue of בר מצרא Bar Metra out
of it for a little bit to just deal with who gets
rights first. Where the בר מצרא Bar Metra is a real rule
that I have rights to the land and I can buy it
from the person without any other discussion, here it's just who gets
first, who has sort of priority in selling land in general. שכינא
דמתא ושכינא דסדא, Shechina de-mata ve-Shechina de-sada,
people who live in the city and people who live outside in
the field. שכינא דמתא קודם. Shechina de-mata kodem. The people who live
in my town have priority. שכן ותלמיד חכם, shachen ve-Talmid Chacham, a
neighbor and a תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham, again we're seeing that the
תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham has special rules. תלמיד חכם קודם. Talmid Chacham
kodem. קרוב ותלמיד חכם, Karov ve-Talmid Chacham,
a relative and a תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham, the תלמיד חכם קודם.
Talmid Chacham kodem. איבעיא להו. Ibaia lehu. Okay
fine, we saw those two cases that the תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham
beats the שכן shachen and the קרוב. karov. What about שכן וקרוב?
shachen ve-karov? Who has priority there? מאי? mai? תא שמע, ta shema,
טוב שכן קרוב מאח רחוק. tov shachen karov me-ach rachok.
We see from the verse in משלי Mishlei that actually שכן shachen
is better. הני זוזי טבי והני זוזי תקולי. Hani zuzei tavei ve-hani
zuzei tekulei. One person has one kind of has better זוזי zuzei
and another person has better coin, it's heavier or better, more useful,
then I can sell it to who I want. לית ביה משום
דינא דבר מצרא. leit bei mishum dina de-Bar Metra.
There's no issue of the דינא דבר מצרא. dina de-Bar Metra. הני
ציירי והני שרי. Hani tzeiri ve-hani shari.
Some have, some are sort of stamped coins and some are not.
לית ביה משום דינא דבר מצרא. leit bei mishum dina de-Bar Metra.
Then I can choose to sell it to the person who has
better who has the better coinage again and so I don't need
to do דינא דבר מצרא. dina de-Bar Metra. This is probably not
things that apply today because whenever we're dealing with money we're simply
dealing with currency, liquid cash, and liquid cash is almost the same
no matter what.
Presumably it would be a difference if somebody wants to pay me
in Euros
because I might make the agreement if somebody wants to pay me
in a different currency it might be a difference because in a
week from now that might be worth less.
But if everybody's coming and paying me dollars, it shouldn't matter to
me. Bitcoin?
I don't know from Bitcoin. אמר, Amar, איזיל ואייתי
זוזי.
Izil ve-aitei
zuzei.
Now we have a different thing.
What about not just like you're coming to me with different coins,
you're coming to me in different situations? What do you say? איזיל
ואייתי זוזי. Izil ve-aitei zuzei.
The בר מצרא Bar Metra comes and says I'm going to go
and try and get money for you. לא נטרינן ליה. Lo natrinan
lei. We don't wait for him. He doesn't have the right to
say I'll have it for you in a week. I need to
go talk to the bank, I need to get a loan, I
need to go sell this thing. I want this land, I need
to sell my car first.
The בר מצרא, Bar Metra, the בר מצרא Bar Metra doesn't have
the right to say that. The בר מצרא Bar Metra has the
right of first refusal to pay right away but he doesn't have
the right of first refusal to say give me a week. No,
I'm trying to sell this now
and that's not טוב וישר. tov ve-yashar. It's not expected?
It's not expected, it's
in order to put this into place, it's required. I don't know,
I think the point is that it's not expected. We have a
דין din of בר מצרא, Bar Metra, we have the ועשית הישר
והטוב, ve-asita ha-yashar ve-ha-tov, we know that we've established that the neighbor
has the right of first refusal. That's a really strong thing. Does
that mean that if I'm in Spain and I have land in
France I have to deal with the בר מצרא Bar Metra in
France? I have estates all over the world. I have to deal
with every בר מצרא Bar Metra to sell all of my, to
sell my estates? If I'm giving it away and I have to
deal with the בר מצרא Bar Metra to give it away to
somebody? No, it doesn't apply all the time. It's going to hurt
me. It's going to make it impossible to actually be מממש memamesh
my rights, to put into place my rights on this land. I
still have rights. You can't be מפסיד mafsid me, you can't hurt
me because of the, because of the hurt that might accrue to
another person.
But there's got to be some notice period? Right, that's the אכרזתא.
achrazata. Right, he has to sell,
yes, that's what we saw earlier when we, later, we don't have
to do אכרזתא. achrazata. We don't have to make an announcement about
it. So there is a period... we don't?
When there's no בר מצרא, Bar Metra, when we say לית ביה
משום, leit bei mishum, we don't have to make an announcement, that
means that there's no בר מצרא Bar Metra or
it's similar to that. Yes, there is a period where I put
it up for sale.
But for somebody to come and say no I want to buy
it or for somebody to say, the לוקח, lokeiach, I want to
buy this from you, it can't be I'm going to get it
to you in a week. I have to give you the money
to get rid of you.
Okay,
however
if it's up for sale, you,
the neighbor can either come in and
take it from the original owner or take it from the לוקח,
lokeiach, buy it
initially, or wait until another buyer comes to set the price?
Yes, although to wait for the other buyer to set the price,
we already saw that it's to some degree his loss if they
bought it at too high a price. If somebody came in and
it's like oh this is worth a hundred... 200, ah, I'm so
excited, it's 200, I'll pay twice as much as it's actually worth.
Now it's worth 200, that's the market value.
And so I, the בר מצרא bar metzra also have to pay
the market value.
Now, there's a difference between איזיל וטרח ואייתי זוזי. izil v'tarach v'ayeiti
zuzei.
I'm going to try to go get this. I'm going to go
try to sell this. But don't keep however, איזיל אייתי
זוזי, izil ayeiti zuzei, I'm going to go get money.
I have
I don't know what I have stock I have a savings account
I have something that I need to liquidate. I'm going to go
get that or simply my coin is stored at my my cash
is stored in a safe somewhere and I need to go get
it is what he's claiming. חזינן, chazinan, we have to sort of
make an make an an estimation. אי גברא דאמיד הוא דאזיל ומייתי
זוזי ee gavra d'amid hu d'azil u'maiti zuzei if this is somebody
who's going to actually go do that, somebody is coming and telling
me I'm going to go get money
and he can, נטרינן ליה ואי לא לא נטרינן ליה. natrinan lei
v'ee lo lo natrinan lei. אלא, ela, if we don't think that
he's somebody, then really he's probably just what we should say is
really he's saying I'm going to go try to get money. Somebody
says and and says I have a meeting with the bank tomorrow
to work out a loan. If this seems to me that some
that this seems like somebody who's going to actually get a loan
from the bank
then okay I wait for you until tomorrow but if this is
somebody who's really just trying to beg the bank for money then
I don't have to wait for you the dear neighbor I'm sorry
you've lost out.
ארעא דחד ובתי דחד. ara d'chad u'vattei d'chad.
Now we have other other issues where who has real priority on
the land of what to do with it.
There's a set there's a piece of land and there's houses on
the land there's buildings on the land there's houses on the land
that people use and people are inhabit but they don't own the
land that their houses are on. We had this difficulty before. There's
a ruin on somebody else's land I come in and rebuild it
what what happens now.
Apparently it was a normal situation that there would be land on
there would be buildings on land that the people didn't own who
lived in them and so rights there are differences in rights when
I don't own the land that I live on. מארי ארעא מעכב
אמרי בתי. marei ara me'akeiv a'marei vattei.
I can stop I have control says the owner of the land
over the people who live in the homes. מארי בתי לא מעכב
אמרי דארעא. marei vattei lo me'akeiv a'marei d'ara.
Rashi explains שלא למכור הבנין לאחר דהוי וזה בעל המצר וזה צריך
לטוב שיהיה בנינו בקרקע שלו ועיקר הישוב יהיה טוב
shelo limkor habinyan l'acher d'havei v'zeh ba'al hametzar v'zeh tzarich l'tov sheyehe
binyano b'karka shelo v'ikar
hayishuv yehe tov that
as if the owner of the land also has sort of a
right as a בר מצרא bar metzra of the building to buy
the building and so I can stop you from selling it to
somebody else but the owner of the building doesn't have the right
doesn't have the right to stop the owner of the land from
selling the land because I don't I don't own the land they're
not really my בר מצרא bar metzra and it's not improper for
me to go sell the land because you live in a house
somewhere in the corner. ארעא דחד ודיקלי דחד. ara d'chad v'diklei d'chad.
Ah
okay fine that was about houses what about trees?
Trees and houses keep coming up as different things that might be
on land that's not owned by them. מארי דארעא מצי מעכב אמרי
דיקלי. marei d'ara matzi me'akeiv a'marei diklei.
I can stop the owners of the of the trees. I sold
them trees on my land sold them for a certain amount of
time for instance maybe and I can't they can't sell to another
person.
מארי דיקלי לא מצי מעכב אמרי דארעא marei diklei lo matzi me'akeiv
a'marei d'ara
but I don't have the right as the owner of as the
owner of a bunch of trees on fruit producing trees on somebody
else's property to stop them selling the field. ארעא לביתי וארעא לזרעי.
ara l'vattei v'ara l'zar'ei.
Okay I'm selling land and I'm going to I have a choice
between selling it to somebody who's going to develop housing and a
choice between somebody who's going to plant it. Which is better? יישוב
עדיף. yishuv adif. Building a development building houses is more important. ולא
מיתיב בה משום דינא דבר מצרא v'lo yasiv bah mishum dina d'bar
metzra and furthermore there's no issue of בר מצרא. bar metzra.
The issue being as Rashi explains ישוב דבתי עדיף לדידין דלא תיקון
כאן עשו הישר והטוב שזו טובה מזו. yishuv d'vattei adif l'didin d'lo
tikkun kan asu hayashar v'hatov shezu tovah mizu.
It's not just that there's טוב לזה ורע לזה, tov l'zeh v'ra
l'zeh, this is act like there are two goods this is this
is good it's good that people should have homes and so it's
more important that you that you have the rights to build homes
on your property for instance what we might conclude from this which
I think was the issue on George Lucas's property that he wanted
to build affordable housing at on his ranch in Marin County and
Marin County really doesn't like affordable housing and so they tried to
stop him and I think in the end he did build it
I'm not sure.
No
here we started out with there was a case of there's land
over here there's a house and what can I sell the house
no I have to sell it to the owner of the land
first can I sell the land yeah sure there's no דינא דבר
מצרא. dina d'bar metzra. Here we're talking about I have a piece
of land, I'm selling it to developers. One is an agricultural developer,
and one is a residential developer. I sell it to the residential
developer because ישוב הארץ. Yishuv Ha'aretz. It's better that people should have
homes than there should be more food.
Was that something about בר מצרא Bar Matzra right now or?
Also we don't have an issue of בר מצרא. Bar Matzra. If
I'm selling it to somebody for building homes, that's better.
Does this apply to like green space and all these kind of
modern?
That's I think a very modern idea that there should be that
sort of thing. And that's also דווקא davka in cities that we
have that idea,
that there should be parks.
Well also there's the whole issue if you cut down forests to
make
houses.
Yeah. Well taking the natural land maybe somebody has some kind of
environmental rights on it. Can they stop that somehow?
Those are not these
are things they probably didn't think that's going to be an issue.
Yeah but it was not open.
Yeah this is not quite the concern we have here. Okay.
Okay. So now we really we finally at the end of us
under this get into like okay so when are you a בר
מצרא Bar Matzra and when are you not? פיסקא משניתא piska mishnita
or ריכבא דדיקלא? richba d'dikla?
What if in between the fields there's sort of like a hedge
of stones or a whole row of trees? Is it really the
field that's next to mine do I really have the same right?
The reason I'm a בר מצרא Bar Matzra is because I want
to expand my same planting field. I want to continue the rows
of thing I want to have more of the same not more
of something else if it's just more of something else then why
am I עדיף adif from somebody else? Why am I preferable? Why
do I have this right?
You don't, we say, if there's a if there's something in between
my field and yours there's a natural fence
of row of stones or a row of trees. חזינא אי יכיל
להכניס בה אפילו תלם אחד איכא משום דינא דבר מצרא ואי לא
ליכא משום דינא דבר מצרא. Chazina i yachil l'hachnis bah afilu telem
echad ika mishum dina d'bar matzra v'i lo leika mishum dina d'bar
matzra. If I can if I can put in a row then
it's like that establishes my right. I have one row of plants
that goes all the way through, I plant other things on the
other side of the hedge, the natural hedge.
We're not talking about bushes, we're talking about trees which would be
a real hassle or loss to cut down and we're talking about
stones which are a huge amount of work to get rid of
to clear the field but if I can get one thing through
that's what establishes my right. It's good for me to continue my
row of plants all the way down the rest of your field
and so I have right of first refusal. If I don't have
that, I don't have right of first refusal and I the owner
of the hedged-in field can sell it to whomever I wish.
Okay. הני ארבעה בני מצרא דקדים חד מינייהו וזבן זביניה זביני. Hani
arba'a bnei metzra d'kadim chad mineihu v'zaven zvinei zvini. If there are
four we have four neighbors, one of them comes and gets there
first, he has first he won. So a question we might have
asked at any point is like how do we there could be
four fields or four fields there's four fields on every side of
me. Who who has rights? Everybody has rights. Who gets? First one
first. כל דאלים גבר Kol d'alim gevar strongest one wins. ואי כולהו
אתו בהדי הדדי פלגו לה בקרנזיל. V'i kulhu atu bahadi hadadi palgu
lah b'karneizil. If everybody comes together,
we split it up sort of diagonally and Rashi thinks that that
means that we have sort of triangle pieces that go in and
there's like a little picture on the side of Rashi which is
I think in everybody's Gemaras
just to put it on the board.
Looks like this. Yep, yep, yep.
And so this person gets that area and this person gets that
area and etc. etc. and that is the end of our discussion
of דינא דבר מצרא Dina D'Bar Matzra in the Gemara
and that will be enough for today.